Essentially, loan the government 100,000 pounds each and hundred
billion pounds collectively. And in return, the government
would guarantee that after ten years or 20 years, it will return this
money with a 3% interest. Now, what have we learned from the previous episode?
The longer you keep this money in the garment, the more interest they'll pay you.
For example, a two year bond could pay you a 3% interest, and a ten
year bond could pay you a 7% interest. So just like
in the previous episode, the demand supply forces will come in. But this
time the primary focus is not the yield curve,
but the cost of borrowing of the government. So let's try
to understand this using a simple example. So let's say there is a ten year
bond that is being sold at 100 pounds per unit at an interest rate of
3%. So if you invest 100 pounds in a ten year bond,
you would get three pounds as interest. Now, listen to this very,
very carefully. Now, if there is nobody willing to
buy these ten year units from the government at hundred pounds,
what will the government do? They would decrease the price of the unit to
90 pounds. So if Shubham bought this unit at 90 pounds,
he would still get three pounds in return. Which means back then,
the garment was borrowing 100 pounds at 3% interest, but now
they are borrowing just 90 pounds at 3.33% interest.
And in spite of this cost drop, if still people don't want to buy these
units or there is an oversupply of these bonds in the market,
the unit price will drop further to 60 pounds, which means now
the government is borrowing 60 pounds at a 5% interest.
So you see, because of the demand supply mismatch, the government is
getting less money from the people at a very, very high
interest rate. And this is a very, very dangerous position for
any government where the interest of the bonds are climbing so high. This is
the reason why the ten year bond rates in the UK have gone up by
almost 300%, going from just above 1% to 4.11%
in just nine months. Now, most people would say, yeah,
bro, so what? The government bonds are now giving out 4% interest, which is absolutely
crazy. So everyone will flock to buy these bonds and the interest rates
will go down, right? So what exactly is the problem? Well,
guess what? Here's where the UK has another problem in the form
of currency depreciation, which makes the bond market of UK
almost useless for big traders. And this is where we have the
currency carry trade that we spoke about in the previous episode. But in
the previous episode, we spoke about the impact of the feds hiking
the interest rate on the currency carry trade. But this time,
let's have a look at what will currency depreciation do to the currency carry
trade. So, let's say William is a billionaire who wants to make money using currency
carry trade in the UK. So what would he do? Firstly,
he would check the lending rates in the US and check the bond market rates
in the UK. So if the US bank is lending at 2% and
the UK bonds are yielding 4%, William will decide to enter the
market. So, firstly, he would borrow $1 million from the US bank.
Secondly, he would convert this $1 million into pounds.
Now, had he made this conversion in January, this would amount to 714,000
pounds. Considering 1.4 to be exchange rate, then he would invest
these 714,000 pounds in the UK bonds and leave
it there for a year. Then, after one year, had it been a normal market,
he would get his 714,000 pounds with a full interest,
which amounts to 742,560 pounds.
Now, he would convert this amount to dollars, which would amount to $1.04
million. So if you look at the interest rate of the feds, he just
has to pay 2% interest to the american bank, as in $1.02 million.
So out of the $1.04 million that he has, he just has to pay 1.02
million and the rest, 0.02 million, will be his profit.
So you see, by simply rotating this money, William was able to
make two in profit. But like I said,
this is the ideal condition. But today, if you look at the market in
UK, the value of pound has depreciated by almost 21.4%
since January. So now the exchange rate is just 1.1.
Now, let's see what happens after one year when William gets 742,560
pounds. When he converts that to dollars, at an exchange rate of 1.1,
he would get only $816,000. But since
the american bank is leaving a 2% interest, he still has to pay 1.02
million to the american bank. Which means what? Even though the bonds are
giving out a 4% interest, because the currency has depreciated
by 21.4%, this currency carry trade has become a
disaster for William. This is what is exactly happening
in the UK, whereby even though the bonds are yielding a 4%
interest, the currency has depreciated to such an extent that
now it has become a disaster for the investors. As a result,
they are quitting the UK market, and this is further decreasing the
demand for pounds. As a result, the currency is depreciating further.
So now that the pound is depreciating, what will happen? The energy prices will
not just spike because of the gas shortage. They will not just spike
because of peak consumption levels during winter, but also because of
currency depreciation. And this will take the cost of energy in the UK to
dangerous levels. And when these energy bills spike up, what will happen?
The government of UK will have to borrow more money in order to compensate for
these losses. Which means more bonds will float in the market,
which means the demand for the bonds will go down, and then the
interest of these bonds will go up, which means the cost of borrowing for
the garment will increase further, eventually depreciating the currency
further, and that will lead to a vicious cycle. On top
of that, they've also announced tax cuts which are expected to decrease the
government revenues by $45 billion till 2026.
So in short, the government of UK is cutting down its own revenues during
a cash crunch situation. This is the reason why everybody is
scared that this scenario will spiral the entire economy
of UK into a freaking disaster. This is the reason why
the bank of England is now about to buy 65 billion pounds worth of
bonds, so that they could prevent the interest rates from falling.
And in the south, with housing loan spikes due to inflation and bank defaults,
it will cause a banking and housing crisis along with energy and
currency crisis. This is the story of the economic crisis
of the UK. So now UK has two options. One is to withdraw the sanctions,
get the gas from Russia and chill. Or secondly, deal with the
complications of its economy by being dependent on the US and hope
that they dont mess up. And this brings me to the most important part
of the episode and that are the study materials to help you understand this economic
crisis in the UK better. But before we move on,
I want to quickly thank our partners of this episode. And that is coding invaders,
people. The international markets have been free falling in the last few
weeks and in conditions like these, there's a high possibility of a job crisis.
But that's where coding invaders come in. They help you switch from non
IT profession to it for high paying jobs within six
to eight months. As a data analyst, their current placement stats stand at 93%.
And the best part is that before you enroll for the course, they provide you
with a guaranteed job agreement with a money back guarantee. So basically,
if you do not get placed, you will get a hundred percent refund.
Their courses have real world business, case studies, job oriented projects
and assignments designed by industry experts from Amazon,
Phillips, Deloitte and others and even a civil engineer like me without
an IT background will be able to learn data science and be eligible for
a high paying IT jobs such as a data analyst. So you
don't need a coding background to get into such jobs. They have helped
20,000 candidates secure 1025 LPA packages in
the past 6.5 months itself with the help of their 300 hiring
partners. So this Diwali you can choose to invest in
yourself rather than the markets. So if this sounds
useful to you, click the link in the description and use the code TS 30
to get 30% fee discount in the job guarantee batch.
Moving on to the study materials, the first thing I am attaching is this 40
page report itself which will teach you about the mini budget. Read through it
and you will understand the other nuances of this crisis.
Secondly, I am attaching the nicer paper that will teach you about the economic
consequence of the energy policy. And I am also attaching a twitter thread
from Anshul who is the co founder of Wind wealth and he has explained the
UK bond crisis even more in depth with simple examples. And lastly,
I am attaching a think school video on the russian gas strategy to choke Europe.
Have a look at that and you will understand. Where did all this episode start
and what is the leverage that Russia has over Europe?
That's all from my side for today guys. If you learned something elaborate, please make
sure to hit the like button in order to support our work so that YouTube
algorithm knows that this video has given value to you. And for more
such insightful business and political case studies, please subscribe to our channel. Thank you
so much for watching. I will see you in the next one. Bye bye.
And don't forget to check out coding invaders from the link in the description.